and, welcome to this session forgetting your apps connected with networking api...my name is
...and aimee program manager in the wireless and core connectivity group.
Before we start I'll give you a quick overview of what is going to be covered in
this session first we'll go over the existing
problems space and prior solutions to those problems then I'll introduce what is new
...windows ten show you some sample code and some demos and then
...you with some next steps for what you could investigate if you're interested in learning more.
So, what is the problem users are not always connected and when
your app requires network connectivity to work its magic that could be a problem so you're
up could...network connectivity for a number of reasons, for example,
your wireless or bluetooth radios could be off you could be in an area within unknown wi-fi
network for which you have to which you have not actually connected yet or you could be in an area with
no wi-fi connectivity at all so prior solutions to this
have been very cumbersome at best on the desktop you had to actually
move the user out of app context in order to fix those problems, for example,
navigating through the settings menu to connect to a wi-fi network or to
...radios on and off or to start internet connection sharing you can also swipe out from the
charms bar to manually connector wireless network on the phone this experience
is somewhat better but it's still not best so on the phone as a windows...one there is the
quick actions toolbar that you can swept down from the top to toggle on the wi-fi and
the to produce manually there's also a...sleep settings link
uri experience where you could go direct the user to another sub page...
I would still require some user interference so in windows ten...to provide some new
api that would make this user experience more seamless and give the developer a little more control over
the user experience so here we have three sets of api is that we are adding
to understand the first of these is radio management api...which
allow developers to toggle the wi-fi and bluetooth radios on and off these aps
...publicly available as long as the developers declare the radios device
capability is also settings page available for letting users manage
this capability which I will show later on the second of these api
is are collectively known as the wi-fi scanned connect api as their name suggest
...allow devices and apps to scan for wi-fi networks within
range and retrieve certain properties such as a society and bs id?
They also allow the apps to connect to common types of wi-fi...
There are some restrictions on these...for example,
the cannot run from a background process but again they are publicly available and
...that which is to use these api is only needs to declare the wi-fi control device
capability you will find this and the windows devices dot wi-fi namespaces and the previous api
...the...you can find in the radio windows dot devices dot radios name
space.
Finally we have the twittering api is also known as mobile hot spot these aren't
entirely knew they were actually existed in windows it up one but they were only available second
party network operators in windows...we're making them publicly available so that any
person or any up developer can start a mobile hot spot on the users device.
So, let's step through a bit of sample code for each of these api
is the first one of these...radio management api...which if we go
through this allows the user to seamlessly toggle on and off the
...without having to go to any settings pages so
two-step to the sample code we first have the request access a
...call which basically allows the app to have access to the
radios in general.
This must be called once
...the why thread in order to...the app access the next call is the get radios
...enumeration call which basically gets all the instances of the
radio's on the system...bluetooth or wi-fi
radios or other on this will be returned analyst.
...if I wanted to turn the wi-fi radio on specifically I would first check to see if
the radio kind was wi-fi and just set state basic to radio state
And, what kinds of apps could find this useful you first of all any...
that needs network connectivity in general but doesn't want to ask the user to go through all this actions to
actually set the radio state on will be useful but they're also certain
...and task cognition apps, for example, which may find these sets of api is very useful to
their scenarios indeed so now I'm going to switch over to my demo for the radio manager
api so here we have the radio manager application to demonstrate the
radio manager aps?
For the purposes of this demonstration I'm going to show the wi-fi
toggle just because you can see the status of it over here in the system...
...go here and turn the wi-fi radio
off should see over here the wi-fi radio has
indeed been turned off I will do the opposite turning it back on and
voila there it goes and I am automatically connected to a...network.
I mentioned before that there's a settings page for managing which apps
have access to this capability if you go to privacy.
...to radio's you should see that there is both a master switchboard controlling whether
apps can set the state of your radios at all as well as the per apps settings toggle so, for example,
if I were to go here toggle the permission off for my radio
manager sdk sample and then I go back here.
Not there to here.
And, I try to
toggle the wi-fi radio again I just can't I do not have access.
So, back to the presentation so now I'll go over some sample code for wi-fi scanning
and wi-fi connecting again we see this request access a...
pattern which allows the apps have access to the wi-fi adopter for any operation
and check the access status see if I have the that permission
...I go through a enumeration pattern this is the windows
are devices
...enumeration pattern for find...a...which is a little bit more roundabout for enumerating
the wi-fi adapters on the system that I'll show simply one later on I say wi-fi
radio's because it's entirely possible for a device or system to have more than one wi-fi
...on...at any time.
So,...here I find a...I
...us query string which is represented here by the wi-fi...dot get device selector
call and then I check to see if I have any results it
turns out if I do have one then I will just take the first...which is returned by this
call usually just default a doctor and then I can go and
...operation so if I go
...the next screen here then you can see some code for actually initiating the scan?
So, I have first adaptor dot scan asic that initiates the driver
scan and populate a list of networks that are within range
...here through the network report attribute so I get a
...the list of the available networks within range and then I can access
each available network and retrieve certain properties such as a society
...signal strength otherwise known as our society and,
channel center frequency there are a whole number of other properties that
are available and you can see them later in the documentation...
So, if you were to use the wi-fi scan api by itself you could use it to
build such applications as a wi-fi channel analyzer which
essentially allows people to determine which frequencies and
...signal strength are best for situated new wireless routers so,
it's entirely possible to use...pies without the connect dpi so.
So, now it to go on to the wi-fi connection portion of this
exercised we have some more sample code using
the available networks that were returned from the wi-fi scanning portion
we are just going to take the first one and let's say that it is
...network that requires a simple password for here for the purposes of this demo I
have the password actually set to password that I hope you don't actually set your password as that civil
string and a create password credential using that ...and that is a
...a well-known class that already exists.
Then I use a connection...operation
to pass in both the available network that was retrieved as a result of the scan operation
the kind of connection that I wanted to be which in this case is permanent not temporary and the
password credentials and then hopefully I'm successful but if not then I want to display to
the user that the connection failed so now I'm going to switch over to the wi-fi
...connect portion of this demo all right so here is the
...scan demo it has
four different scenarios and only going to demonstrate the second and fourth one scanning connect respectively
...over here...the wonderful scan button.
So, I see...networks that has been returned by the scan.
Very simple straightforward you can see that it has given me various properties like the...societies
at the routers that...and frequency and the encryption type also shows me whether I'm
connected to that specific network you switch over to scenario for here connect.
To the scan button again and then actually do something with the information that the scan results return so I'm
going to go and connect to nsf...open.
And, as you can see here it doesn't require password I can choose whether not to auto reconnect I'm just going to go in
hadn't
kicked hit connect see here that I was momentarily without connectivity
but now I m connected to a wi-fi network which is pretty cool.
So, I'm going to switch back to the presentation...we have some sample code for the
...api is also known as mobile hot
spot I don't have a demo for this but this has existed since windows it...can
...more sample apps there if necessary the tether api allow
...app to share its internet connection over so the cellular radio and
...connection with other devices so the windows ten api
...will allow apps to seamlessly start sharing their mobile hot spot with other devices
so the first step in this sequence of calls here is to create a
...manager we've set want to know because we're not sure if we are connected to sell
yet that is the first check that proceeds in this bit of sample code here
so I see if I have a internet connection profile currently and then I check
to see if it is a w when connection profile another name for the
...connection so if I am indeed connected and if I do have
...over cellular than I can retreat a new
...manager and created from that connection profile the next step in this
is to try actually connecting where to start...
So, have...manager dot start covering a
...and then I can check to see whether that operations fails or succeeded?
So, that is all the api is that I had to
show if you're interested in learning more later on you can follow the links within this presentation to find
some msdn documentation and sample apps for the windows ten
...and finally if you're interested in learning more about the connectivity and networking
solutions offered in windows ten then I recommend you check out the wi-fi direct
and wi-fi direct services talk linked below thank you very much and I hope you enjoyed this presentation.